Finding Aid for Whittemore Family Papers, 1817-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Whittemore Family Papers 1817-1978
Whittemore Family (Tawas City, Mich.)
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
5 linear feet
86261 Aa 2; AC; Ac
Gideon O. Whittemore family of Pontiac and Tawas City, Michigan. Business and personal correspondence of Whittemore, his wife, their son James O. Whittemore, and other members of the Whittemore, Mack, and Abram Mathews families; also business and legal documents, sermons, photographs, and miscellaneous papers, covering family matters, Tawas City, Michigan (which the family founded), lumbering, journey of the Mormons across the United States and settlement in Salt Lake City, Utah, University of Michigan and its branches, and family genealogy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 1161 ) has come to the library in several accessions beginning in 1938 with a gift from W. Frank Whittemore. Additional papers came from Professor Harlow O. Whittemore in 1958.
The collection is open to research.
The Whittemore family, led by Gideon O. Whittemore, were founders of the town now known as Tawas City, Michigan. As men of business, they lumbered, milled, and sold the pine timber on their land then known as Ottawas Bay on Lake Huron. They were also civically responsible, serving their local community and the state in various capacities.
Gideon Olin Whittemore was born August 12, 1800 in St. Albans, Vermont. He came to Michigan in 1820 and in 1826, began practicing law in Pontiac. During his time there, Gideon Whittemore held many offices of trust in Oakland County as well as the state, and was at one time or another the Secretary of State, a member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents and the State Board of Education. On Feb. 13, 1828 he married Mrs. Harriet Mack Hatch, the daughter of his former employer, Colonel Stephen Mack of Detroit and his wife Temperance Bond Mack.
In 1853, Gideon Olin Whittemore left Pontiac and made an exploratory visit to the Tawas Bay area. He purchased 5,300 acres of land, which included the mouth of the Tawas River, and with two business partners, James Covert of Albany and his daughter Harriet Frances Mathews, began harvesting the trees on his land as well as operating a steam saw mill. A. B. Mathews, the husband of Whittemore's daughter Harriet, was also active in the business as were Gideon's sons, James Olin Whittemore, a younger brother Charles Hanover Whittemore, and the youngest son William Bond Whittemore. Gideon Olin Whittemore died in June of 1863, followed by his daughter Harriet Frances Mathews in 1866, and his wife Harriet Mack Whittemore in 1872.
James O. Whittemore was born December 3, 1828 in Pontiac, Michigan. He began college in 1843 at the Pontiac branch of the University of Michigan. He continued his studies in Ann Arbor where he graduated in 1846. After graduation, he became book-keeper for Mathews and Co. of Rochester, Michigan. He taught school in Hillsdale, Michigan and in the South (Kentucky, 1851-1852) and (Georgia, 1853-1854). He returned to Michigan making Tawas and Iosco County his home; and in 1856 he married Melissa Sarah Starkweather. In Tawas Whittemore practiced law and served his community in various capacities: as postmaster of the first post office between Bay City and Mackinac (Tawas in 1856), as county clerk, register of deeds, and judge of probate. He died June 7, 1889.
William Franklin Whittemore, son of James Olin Whittemore and Melissa Starkweather, married Jessie Estella Lyon, daughter of James Monroe Lyon and Anna (Harlow) Lyon. Their son was Harlow Olin Whittemore, a landscape architect and professor of landscape architecture at the University of Michigan.
The papers date from 1817 to 1978, and include correspondence, business papers, deeds, genealogical materials, photographs and other papers of Gideon O. Whittemore, his wife, their son James Olin Whittemore and other member of the Whittemore, Mack, Harlow, and Abram Mathews families. Letters of Temperance Mack and Almira Covey document in part the journey of the Mormons across the United States and settlement in Salt Lake City. Other papers relate to activities in Tawas City (which the family founded), lumbering interests, and other business matters. A portion of the papers of James Olin Whittemore pertain to his activities as a student at the University of Michigan, class of 1846.
The Whittemore family collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Other Family papers; Genealogical records; Temperance Mack letters and related; Individual Whittemore family members; Photographs; and Business and professional ledgers and daybooks.
Subjects:
Band of the Broken Pipes (University of Michigan); Coonent, James.; Detroit and Pontiac Railroad Company.; Hatch, Henry.; Hatch, Rufus, 1785-1825.; Hillsdale (Mich.); Iosco County (Mich.); Land use--Michigan--Iosco County.; Leach, DeWitt C., b. 1832.; Logging--Michigan--Tawas City.; Lumbering--Michigan--Tawas City.; Mack, John M.; Mack, Stephen, 1762-1826.; Mack, Temperance, d. 1850.; Mathews, Abram B.; Mathews, Harriet Francis, d. 1866.; Michigan State University--History.; Mormons.; Nauvoo (Ill.); Pontiac (Mich.); Railroads--Michigan.; Roads--Michigan.; Salt Lake City (Utah); Schools--Georgia.; Schools--Kentucky.; Schools--Michigan.; Shipping--Great Lakes (North America); Tawas City (Mich.)--Commerce.; Teachers--Georgia.; Teachers--Kentucky.; Teachers--Michigan--Hillsdale.; Temperance--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Tobacco.; United States. Army. New York Cavalry Regiment, 20th (1863-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. College of Natural History.; University of Michigan. College Temperance Society.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Utah.; Whitmore family.; Whittemore, Charles Hanover, b. 1833.; Whittemore, George, 1831-1844.; Whittemore, Gideon Olin, 1800-1863.; Whittemore, William B., b. 1835.; Wisner, Moses, 1815-1863.; Women--Michigan--Tawas City.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
California.; Courthouses--Michigan--Tawas City.; Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ovid.; Dwellings--Michigan--Tawas City.; Iosco County Courthouse (Tawas City, Mich.); Ovid (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Tawas City (Mich.)--Courthouses.; Tawas City (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Tombs & sepulchral monuments.; Whitmore family.
Contributors:
Harlow, Charles.; Mason, Stevens Thomson, 1811-1843.; Mayhew, Ira, 1814-1894.; Meade, George Gordon, 1815-1872.; Morgan, Gilbert.; Pitcher, Zina, 1797-1872.; Smith, Hyrum, 1800-1844.; Trowbridge, Rowland E., 1821-1881.; Whipple, Charles Whiley, 1805-1855.; Whittemore, James Olin, 1828-1889.; Whittemore, W. Frank.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Sermons.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence (mainly family letters)
  The Correspondence series consists mainly of letters exchanged among family members and business associates. Although the files date from 1817 to 1845, the great bulk of the papers are in the period of approximately 1830 to 1870. Of interest are the letters written by James O. Whittemore while teaching school in Kentucky and Georgia in the period of 1851-1854.
  - Undated (Box 1)
    (include anti-alcohol pledge)
  - 1817-1827 (Box 1)
    (include Stephen Mack obituary 1826)
  - 1828-1834 (Box 1)
  - 1835-1836 (Box 1)
  - 1837-1838 (Box 1)
    (include letters from Gilbert Morgan and Zina Pitcher relating to difficulties of establishing proposed branches of the University of Michigan, 1837 also letter from Stevens T. Mason)
  - 1839-1844 (Box 1)
  - 1845 (Box 1)
  - 1846-1848 (Box 1)
  - 1849-1850 (Box 1)
    (includes letters relating to James O. Whittemore teaching at Hillsdale, 1850)
  - 1851 (Box 1)
  - 1852-1853 (Box 1)
  - 1854 (Box 1)
  - 1855 (Box 1)
    (include letters relating to relating to the locating of a State Agricultural College in East Lansing)
  - 1856 (Box 1)
  - 1857 (Box 1)
  - 1858 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1859 (Box 1)
  - March 1859 (Box 1)
  - April-May 1859 (Box 1)
  - June-July 1859 (Box 1)
  - August-September 1859 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1859 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1860 (Box 1)
    (include letter from Governor Moses Wisner relating to the building of a state road)
  - March-May 1860 (Box 1)
  - June-July 1860 (Box 1)
  - August 1860 (Box 1)
    (include letter from George Meade relating to the publication of a chart of Saginaw Bay)
  - September-October 1860 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1860 (Box 1)
  - 1861 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1862 (Box 1)
  - May-September 1862 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1862 (Box 1)
  - 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - 1866 (Box 1)
  - 1868-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1874 (Box 1)
  - 1877-1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1945 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous handwritten copies of family letters 1819-1868 (Box 1)
    (the copies were transcribed in 1933)
- Other family papers: indentures for land, warranty deeds, etc.
  The Other Family Papers series contains land acquisition documents, financial miscellanea such as receipts and accounts, and various writings. These files have been arranged chronologically except for a small set of files that includes clippings, poetry, a sermon, and a map.
  - By date
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1818-1832 (Box 1)
    - 1833-1834 (Box 1)
    - 1835-1836 (Box 1)
    - 1837-1838 (Box 1)
    - 1839 (Box 1)
    - 1840-1841 (Box 1)
    - 1842-1844 (Box 1)
      (include memorandums of travels from Pontiac to Iowa and includes descriptions of Commerce, Milford, Hamburg, Dexter, Jackson, the State Prison, Homer, Union City, Centerville, Constantine and Mottville, Michigan; also parts of Indiana and Illinois, including Nauvoo, June 1843 ?)
    - 1846-1850 (Box 1)
    - 1851-1853 (Box 1)
    - 1854 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1855 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1855 (Box 1)
    - 1856 (Box 1)
    - 1857 (Box 1)
    - 1858 (Box 1)
    - 1859 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1860 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1860 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1861 (Box 2)
    - July-December 1861 (Box 2)
    - 1862 (Box 2)
    - 1867-1874 (Box 2)
    - 1877-1934 (Box 2)
  - Land documents (Folder 1)
    (includes land indentures and land grant to Luther Jones, January 3, 1831)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Certificates, printed items, ephemera, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    - Poems, miscellaneous undated (Box 2)
    - Sermons (Box 2)
    - Tawas City, map (Folder 1)
      (in oversize folder Ac)
- Genealogical records
  The Genealogical records series includes extensive information about the various branches of the Whittemore family. Included is "Genealogy of Several Branches of the Whittemore Family: Including the Original Whittemore Family of Hitchin, Hertfordshire, England: And a Brief Lineage of Other Branches," written by B.B. Whittemore and "History of the Whittemore Family of Michigan" This last volume, prepared by William F. Whittemore and his son Harlow O. Whittemore, genealogical material on the Whittemore family from 1086-1641 in England; 1641-1937 in New England & Michigan; and from 1937-1972 on the Whittemore families in Michigan and elsewhere.
  - Letters about family history written to W. F. Whittemore 1922-1942 (Box 2)
  - Genealogy of Several Branches of the Whittemore Family 1893, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Historical and Family Record Books, 1 oversize volumes; 4 volumes (Box 2)
    (include reminiscences, transcripts of letters, photos, etc.)
  - History of the Whittemore Family in Michigan written by W. Franklin and Harlow O. Whittemore 1970s undated (Box 2)
  - General material circa 1930s (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Temperance Mack letters and related
  Within the collection there are letters of Temperance Mack and her daughter, Mrs. Almira Covey, which document in part the journey of the Mormons across the United States and settlement in Salt Lake City. Several of the letters were written from Nauvoo, Illinois in the 1840s. There are also letters from Hyrum Smith (Mrs. Harriet Mack Whittemore's cousin) with information about Temperance Mack and Mrs. Almira Covey.
  - Letters of Temperance Mack, Almira Covey and Hyrum Smith 1835-1849, 23 items (in 2 folders); photostatic copies
    [Note: originals have been placed in library vault; a negative microfilm of these letters is also available]
    - 1835-1842
      - Prayer fragment undated (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira Scobey, Liberty, Mo. March 10, 1835 (Box 2)
        (She later became Almira Covey)
      - Letter, Almira Scobey, Liberty, Mo. June 9, 1835 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Pottawattamie, Iowa May 16, 1838 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Harvey Woodworth, Painesville, Ohio May 28, 1838 (attached with copy of note by David Dort and Temperance Mack, January 24, 1839) (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Far West, Mo. December 30, 1838 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Nauvoo, Ill. September 16, 1841 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira Covey, Nauvoo, Ill. February 11, 1842 (Box 2)
    - 1843-1849
      - Obituary of Colonel Stephen Mack 1843 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Hyrum Smith, Nauvoo April 9, 1843 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Nauvoo, Ill. October 23, 1843 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira Covey and Temperance Mack, Nauvoo, Ill. December 9, 1843 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira Covey, Nauvoo, Ill. May 19, 1844 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira Covey, Nauvoo, Ill. January 5, 1845 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira Covey, Nauvoo, Ill. October 21, 1845 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Nauvoo, Ill. October 21, 1845 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Almira, Nauvoo, Ill. December 8, 1845 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Nauvoo, Ill. January 10, 1846 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Mt. Pinga June 30, 1846 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack May 5, 1847 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Winter Quarters June 22, 1847 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack, Salt Lake City March 20, 1849 (Box 2)
      - Letter, Temperance Mack and Almira Covey, Salt Lake City October 8, 1849 (Box 2)
  - Listing of Birthdates of Children of Colonel Stephen Mack and Temperance Bond Mack 1788-1808 (Box 2)
  - Progenitors and Descendants of Colonel Stephen Mack and Temperance Bond Mack 1975 (Box 2)
- Individual family members
  The Individual family members series consists of papers of the following family members: Gideon O. Whittemore, James O. Whittemore, William F. and Jessie Whittemore, Douglas M. Whittemore, and members of the Harlow family. Papers for James O. Whittemore pertain to his activities as a student at the University of Michigan, class of 1846. In addition to student essays, these papers include materials about student organizations, notably the College Temperance Society and the Band of Broken Pipes, an anti-tobacco student organization. Also of note is a diary of Charles Harlow, a member of the 20th New York Cavalry, Co. D during the Civil War.
  - Whittemore, Gideon O.
    - Appointment of Gideon O. Whittemore as Regent of the University of Michigan signed by Stevens T. Mason March 1836 (Folder 1)
  - Whittemore, James Olin
    - Diary 1866-1867 (Box 2)
    - Transcript of the diary made in 1932 (Box 2)
    - Speeches and Certificates (and miscellaneous materials) 1846-1875 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan student materials
      - Student Essays 1844-1845 (Box 2)
      - Band of Broken Pipes (University of Michigan anti-tobacco student organization) 1845 (Box 2)
      - College Temperance Society (University of Michigan student organization) 1844 (Box 2)
      - College of Natural History (University of Michigan) 1845 (Box 2)
  - Whittemore, William F. and Jessie (wife) papers
    - Diary 1936 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - To W. F. W. 1883-1939 (Box 3)
      - To Jessie W., undated 1909, 1919, 1927, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Douglas W. (son) to W. F. W. and J. W. 1927 (Box 3)
      - James O. Whittemore to W. F. W. 1885-1888 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 3)
  - Whittemore, Douglas M.
    - Biography by his brother Harlow Whittemore undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - To D. W. 1919, 1920, 1925 (Box 3)
      - From Jessie W., Harlow W., and Philip Dow 1927 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 3)
  - Harlow Family members
    (W. Frank Whittemore's wife family)
    - Anna Harlow diary 1864 (Box 3)
    - Charles Harlow diary 1863-1865 (Box 3)
      (Harlow served as member of 20th New York Cavalry, Co. D; he was also musician)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes family portraits; and photographs of family homes in Tawas City and Ovid, Michigan, and San Diego, California.
  - Temperance Mack gravesite undated (Box 3)
  - Mathews family undated (Box 3)
  - Residences of James F., Lyman C., and William F. Whittemore, Tawas City, circa 1895 (Box 3)
  - Tawas City area 1880-1890, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Starkweather family--Image of William F. Whittemore's grandmother (Box 3)
  - Whittemore family members undated
    - Gideon O. Whittemore undated (Box 3)
    - Jessie Whittemore's ancestors undated (Box 3)
    - Olin Whittemore undated (Box 3)
  - Unidentified people undated
    - Two positives (Box 3)
    - One negative (Box 3)
  - Family portrait albums, post Civil War, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    (some images identified)
- Business and professional ledgers and daybooks
  The Business and professional ledgers and daybooks series consists of daybooks and a ledger of Gideon O. Whittemore's mercantile lumbering accounts; and financial records and a letter book from James O. Whittemore as businessman and in his role as county clerk and postmaster.
  - Gideon O. Whittemore daybooks and ledger 1854, 1864-1868, 1 folders; 4 volumes (Box 5)
  - James O. Whittemore daybooks, ledgers, and cash book, letter book 1867-1882, 7 volumes (Box 5)
Related Material
The library also has a separate collection of the papers of Harlow Olin Whittemore, a landscape architect and professor of landscape architecture at the University of Michigan